这是星际运输网络 你觉得我能靠它回家吗?
This is an interplanetary transport network! And you think I can reach my home planet?
"我觉得……可能吧?"
J.: "I mean, probably?!"
就是这个感觉!
That's the spirit!
而这是我用来解决复杂航天问题的概率追踪工具
And this is my probability tracer solving tough spaceflight riddles.
在优化燃料与时间的前提下 最优的回家路径是哪条?
What's the best path home, optimizing fuel and time?
这是一个极其复杂的动态组合混合问题
That's an insane dynamical/combinatorial mixed problem.
解决这个问题的过程中 大家会学会使用流形 弱稳定边界
And as we solve it, you learn to use manifolds, weak stability boundaries,
周期轨道等众多航天动力学工具
periodic orbits, and many more spaceflight tools.
大家可能还未见过这些展示方式
All shown in ways you probably haven't seen before.
我们从构建追踪器开始
And we start with building the tracer.
希望能成功吧……毕竟我的朋友还等着我去营救呢
I.. hope to get it right. Because my friend needs a rescue.
不是我说 您是怎么飞到这来的? 燃料都快用光了 完犊子了
I'm not judging, but how do you get here .. running low on everything: the journey is over.
不过拿来当案例还不错——迷失在外太空该怎么办!
Still, it's a great example of what to do when lost in outer space!
① 为何"回家"会如此困难
Step one: What makes "getting home" so hard?
想象茫茫太空中只有你和你的航天器
Imagine nothing else but you in a spaceship.
从A点飞到B点轻而易举
Getting from here to there is peanuts.
点火 直线漂过去就好
Fire and drift along a straight path.
这时加个星球 你就跑偏了
Let's add a planet, and you swing by.
这条路径是最优的吗? 好好想想啦!
Is it still a great path? Look into the future!
这样的二体问题可以求出解析解
And for this two-body constellation, looking means solving analytic expressions.
非常简单 给出参数 就能得到对应的开普勒轨道
Which are pretty simple – give parameters, and you get the Keplerian orbits.
虽然不太能看出来 但星球本身也在围绕两者的重心旋转
Now, you can't see it, but the planet moves around the gravitational center, too.
能量守恒 动量守恒
Energy and momentum conservation.
增加一个大质量天体后会更明显一点
You will see it by adding more massive planets.
但除特殊情况外 很难能找到数学上简单的闭合解
But except for some motions, you rarely find these simple mathematically closed-form expressions.
有了电脑的帮助
Now we all have computers.
就有了多个物体路径预测的方法: 数值积分
So, there is an easy prediction method for many masses: numerical time integration.
方法很简单 根据当前重力 来预测速度的微小变化
The idea is simple. Take the current gravitational forces to guess tiny velocity changes.
根据当前速度 来预测位移的微小变化
And take the current velocities to guess tiny location changes.
也就是牛顿运动定律
You guessed it: Newton's laws of motion.
这种步进的运算会积累误差 且会花计算机不少时间
This stepwise computation is prone to errors and takes your computer some time.
该方法可以把模拟分成两部分来优化计算速度
Now, there is a tweak to speed up the computation by splitting the simulation.
相对天体 航天器质量很小 对天体运动的影响也很小
The spaceship is lightweight compared to the planets, and so is its impact on their motion.
所以第一次运算不带入航天器 只保存天体的运动路径
So, make a first run without the spaceship and store the paths.
第二次运算直接回放天体的运动路径 从而计算航天器的路径
And then, play back the planet's motion in the next run to get the spaceship's reaction.
对于计算大量航天器的路径 这种方法会快得多
That's much faster in total if you want to compute many spaceships anyway.
每次模拟只需计算航天器相对其它三个星球的重力影响 不错吧?
Each new simulation only moves one spaceship pulled by three gravitational forces. Sounds great?
有意思的来了
Here is the kicker.
要想确认这条路径能不能用 就要进行预测
To see if a path is a winner, predict the future.
但对于单个航天器来说 时间跨度越长 预测难度越大
Which, even for just one simulated spaceship, gets harder the longer the journey.
画面中例子 只改变极其微小的速度 就能极大影响未来路径
Here, I fire a little bit, and my route zaps all over the place!
在充满未知的真实世界 太远的预测可信度不高
With all the uncertainties about the real world, longer simulations are hard to trust.
但其实不需考虑这种问题
But no need for thrust issues here.
我可以随时点火来调整自己的轨迹 对吧?
I can fire anytime to tune the path and make a different winner, right?
话是这样讲 那么下个问题——怎样点火才是最优解?
Absolutely, but the next question is: what is the best firing?
比如飞行时间受限 燃料消耗受限
Say you are short on travel time and propellant consumption.
想要得到最优解 你需要遍历所有时间点的所有可能的点火
To get the optimal route: You have to search along all possible firings at any time!
每时每刻都要做决策!
That's a continuum of decisions!
就不能最开始进行一次点火 然后什么都不做吗?
Simply firing initially and then doing nothing can't be the whole story?
而对于我朋友 他也有一个简单的方法回家
Oh, and for my friend here, there is an easy way home.
当他飞到图中位置时 相对丝带星 向前点火 降低和太阳的相对速度
译注: 视频中星球都是虚构的
Silk 丝带星
Blue 蓝星
Yellow 黄星
Fire relative to planet Silk in prograde direction at this point to slow down relative to the Sun.
稍等片刻——
Wait a little bit.
到达蓝星轨道
Reach planet Blue's orbit.
相对蓝星 反向点火减速 进入蓝星环绕轨道
Fire retrograde relative to Blue to slow down while falling into an orbit around Blue.
然后着陆 任务完成!
From here on land! It's that easy.
要不还能怎么回家?
And seriously, how else to get home?
这是霍曼转移 据我所知 这是一条理想的转移轨道
That's a Hohmann transfer, which I learned makes an ideal transfer orbit.
问题在于 这条轨道消耗太大
The problem is, it's too costly here.
燃料早在进入"近蓝星轨道"的点火中就耗尽了
Propellant runs out during the 'Low Blue Orbit' 'injection burn.'
那有没有更好的流程?
So, what's the better sequence?
我们来对比下所有可能的返回路径 考虑所有可能的中途点火
Let's compare all possible paths home, considering all possible intermediate firings.
剧透一下——可能的连续点火实际上很有用
Spoiler: The continuity of firing possibilities actually helps.
再剧透一下——通过几次特殊的试验 低能量路径会自动显现出来
Spoiler spoiler: running special experiments, low-energy routes will come up automatically.
也不要慌张 我搞的这个太阳系 尺寸和质量都很灵活
And don't panic! I keep this playground solar system flexible in sizes and masses.
我希望同时展现局部和全局的运动 因为这个系统主要目的是科普
I want to see all local and global action at once. Because this system revolves around education.
② 轨迹有什么缺陷?
Step two: what's wrong with rays?
先别管点火的事情 因为点火会创造新的轨迹
Forget about firing for now, that's like spawning new rays.
首先 轨迹追踪就存在问题 我来举个例子
There is a problem with ray tracing in the first place. I give an example.
假如你在进行重力助推机动 也叫引力弹弓
Say you perform a gravity assist maneuver, aka swing-by.
引力弹弓前后 相对行星的速度值不变 方向改变
The speed before and after the swing-by won't change relative to the planet, but the path direction will.
而相对于太阳 速度与轨道的能量都会改变 让你能飞得更远
Relative to the Sun, this changes the speed and the orbital energy: you can reach farther out.
问题出现了——重力弹弓后 轨迹簇的分辨率降低了
And here is the problem: After the swing-by, the resolution of the ray package is lost.
虽说这种发散没什么坏处 反而对路径控制有好处
Now, honestly, this spreading is nothing bad. It's great for route controlling.
但会出现很多未受到采样的区域
But it generates more non-sampled space between the rays.
虽然可以增加轨迹数量来填充未采样区域
To fill in the details, shoot more rays.
但这并没有改变采样分辨率失衡的事实 导致很容易错过最优解
But it doesn't solve the unbalanced resolution. It's easy to miss a winner.
可不可以放弃轨迹追踪 改为概率追踪?
So why don't we build not a ray tracer but a probability tracer?
把航天器位置概率置于计算网格中
Let's push spaceship-position probabilities over a computational grid.
均匀的计算结果让可达的目标点可以被一眼看出
This gives a numerically equalized look, and if a target is reachable, you see it!
③ 追踪航天器的概率
Step three: tracing spaceship probabilities
首先我们要弄清楚一点 追踪概率其实在解答另一个问题
First, let's get this right: tracing probabilities answers a different question.
不是精确查找某条路径 而是判断是否存在这样的路径
You don't look for precise routes but whether there are any routes.
这样你就知道是否值得重建一条最优路径了
And then you know if it's worth reconstructing a winner.
因此 只需把概率云放在空间网格上
So, all I need is a probability cloud that lives on a spatial grid.
让算法调整网格值 就能展现无穷多的航天器轨迹了对吧?
And the algorithm tunes grid values to show whatever infinitely many spaceships do. Awesome, right?
错啦
Well, that's impossible.
考虑两块概率云重叠的情况
Think of two probability clouds overlapping.
什么也没发生 两者擦肩而过 怎会如此?
Nothing happens. They pass without interaction. And why should they?
它们代表了无穷多各自独立的航天器
They represent infinitely many independent spaceships.
发现问题了吗?
I hope you see the problem?
两朵概率云以不同的速度矢量重叠
Both clouds overlap with different velocity vectors.
那么哪一个才能指导基于位置的算法如何调整网格值呢?
So, which one tells the position-based algorithm how to shift the grid values?
该听哪个矢量的?
Which vector wins?
或者说 如何区分哪朵概率云的速度?
Or, for that matter, how to even tell each cloud its velocity?
很显然 基于位置的描述没有足够的空间来处理任意多值的速度
It's simple: A position-based description contains not enough space to handle arbitrarily multi-valued velocities.
概率云应该存在于位置与速度的空间中 即相空间
The probability lives in position and velocity space – the phase space.
相空间的大小要看具体问题 我举个例子
And don't think of one magical phase space size it depends on the problem. I give you an example.
这1000个点 会映射到4000维相空间内的一个点
These 1,000 particles make one point in a 4,000-dimensional phase space.
每个坐标都存储了某个粒子的独特信息
Each coordinate stores unique information about some particle.
你可以把一点变成一个模糊的小云 整体考虑实验的无限多种变化
You can make this point a blurred blob to think collectively about infinitely many variations of this experiment.
重点来了
And here is the key.
与其在高维的N粒子相空间中追踪概率
Instead of tracing probabilities in this high-dimensional n-particle phase space,
不如考虑给定位置和速度范围内 找到粒子的可能性有多大
ask how likely to find any particle to be in a given location and velocity range.
我们可以在与航天器相同的相空间中追踪概率
You can chase the probability in the same phase space as that of the spaceship.
但航天器的概率云重叠时没有自相互作用
However, while the spaceship probability passes without self-interaction,
而流体有 概率也显示了这一点
the fluid does, and the probability shows it.
足够多的相互作用
With enough particle interaction,
导致粒子们可以被取决于位置的物理量描述
达到了局部热力学平衡
they struggle themselves to effectively 2-dimensional behavior – they equilibrate locally.
导致粒子们可以被取决于位置的物理量描述
达到了局部热力学平衡
And then, position-based fields make sense: temperature, pressure, or probability.
退化成四个无自相互作用的场 需要一四维向量来描述每个位置的物理量
Reduce to non-self-interaction, and you need a four-dimensional grid.
因此 等离子体或流体领域因其自身原因难度不低
So, the plasma or fluid side of the spectrum are challenging for their own reasons.
但它们也有自己的求解方法 值得我们借鉴
But they also come with their own solution methods that we can steal.
虽然这并不容易 比如这个例子:
But it won't be easy! Watch this!
该模拟跑在200乘200网格的位置空间上……
This simulation runs on the huge amount of 200 x 200 cells …
同时还有200……乘200网格的速度空间
by 200 cells … by 200 cells.
总共16亿的网格才能计算这一块小云?
1.6 billion cells to get this blocky blob?
我本想进行全面的统计分析 但现在看来实在力不从心
I was hoping for a full-blown statistical analysis, but it's getting out of reach!
可是想要研究流形 我需要这样的追踪器啊
I mean, to investigate my manifolds, I need a tracer.
别急 这还没完
Don't worry, things get worse.
考虑一维势阱中的一个航天器
Imagine a spaceship in one dimension within a potential well.
离两侧越近 指向中心的力越大
The closer it gets to the sides, the more it pushes back.
它的相空间是二维的: 位置与速度
The phase space has two dimensions: one for position and one for velocity.
而概率密度小云表示势阱中无穷多的航天器
And a probability density blob reflects infinitely many spaceships.
注意看 随着时间推移 这些概率云会混叠
Now, look at this. As time passes, the probability mixes.
可是每次追踪所处的局部概率密度是定值
Yet, per tracer, the probability density stays constant.
它不会随着相邻值的变化而扩散
It doesn't diffuse with neighbor values.
而是位置与速度相互补偿
The motion along position and velocity compensate each other,
(刘维尔定理)
任意的相空间体积元的体积大小保持不变
and arbitrary phase-space volumes are conserved.
因此 小云会无压缩地流动 不出现概率扩散 包含无限的细节
So, this blob moves incompressibly, generating infinite details without probability diffusion.
但远看仿佛它扩散了一样
It looks like diffusion if you don't look precisely, though.
这就是问题所在
And that's the problem.
我的算法中 数值都是在网格中存储的 并没有看上去那么精确
My algorithm just stores grid values – it doesn't look precisely.
每次更新数值 需要追溯概率的来源
To update these, you trace back where the probability came from.
而这很可能在网格之间的某个地方
Which likely was somewhere between grid points.
所以就要去猜测这些数值
So you have to guess these values.
导致数值模糊或扩散
This gives numerical softening or diffusion.
那为什么还要费事用概率追踪呢?
Then, why bother with all this?
因为与轨迹追踪相比 概率追踪能保持分辨率
Well, compared to ray tracing, you equalize the resolution.
在底层仍使用的是结构化的分段
Although, under the hood, it uses structured ray segments.
但插值还是会破坏精度
But the interpolation breaks the accuracy.
那我这套统计天体动力学注定要破灭了吗?
So, is all my hope in statistical astrodynamics doomed to diffuse?
细细想来 这个结果和之前随机点火的航天器是不是很像?
Thinking about it, doesn't it look like randomly firing – that I have to implement anyway?
另外 我实际想要的并不是概率 而是可达性
Also, I don't need the probability but the reachability.
能不能到家 能还是不能!
Do you get home – yes or no!
④ 追踪航天器的可达性
Step 4: tracing spaceship reachability
注意 数值扩散虽看起来和随机点火很像
Careful! Numerical diffusion can look like random firing.
但概率的扩散并不相同——概率总是沿着相流扩散
But the probability blurs differently – mainly along the phase space flow.
而随机点火意味着存在加速度
Random firing, however, means acceleration,
所以它会沿着速度的方向扩散 然后再向位置方向扩散
so it blurs along the velocity axis, which then translates into position blurs.
这一微小区别很重要
And this tiny distinction matters.
我们在意"可达性" 因为到达蓝星时是有额外条件的
We care about reachability but in phase space, you don't want to reach planet Blue's location at any cost.
因为还有一个速度窗口
You have a velocity window to reach as well.
这里在计算上有一个捷径
Now, there is a computational shortcut to handle that.
考虑一维空间中想到达这个白点的航天器
Think about reaching this spot with the one-dimensional spaceship.
随机点火的结果中 很多航天器都能到达目标
Random firing makes many spaceships reach the goal.
但最快的那个 始终沿着小云的边界前进
But the fastest ones travel on the blob's boundary.
它通过持续点火 让小云以最快速度扩张
They keep expanding the blob the fastest by firing continuously.
本例中 最快的方法就是朝向目标点火 然后再反向点火刹车
Here, for the fastest way, fire towards the goal and then fire backwards.
现实中的电推发动机就是这样持续点火的
Now, there are electrical engines built to fire continuously.
它们以较小推力 长时间点火飞行
Essentially, they generate a relatively low thrust over a long period of time.
相反 化学燃料发动机推力更大 点火时长更短
In contrast, chemical engines give higher thrust for shorter periods of time.
这样 等稍后我解决连续点火的问题时 只需追踪边界即可
So, when I later solve a continuous firing problem, I just need to trace the boundary – great!
意识到这点后 我打算构建一个基于网格的精确边界追踪
And realizing this, I wanted to build an exact grid-based boundary tracer.
我把它放在了更长版本的视频中
I put it in a longer version of this video.
我成功了一部分 但看起来无间隙预测总会带来扩散
And I partly managed to make it work, but it looks like a gap-free prediction implies diffusion.
整个网格的制作过程真是一团乱麻
Making this whole grid thing is a debacle.
而我也有所体会 想造出我想要的追踪算法 总要有些牺牲
And I get the hint: To get my tracer, I have to sacrifice.
⑥ 构建Spray追踪
Step 6: Building spray tracers.
回到开始 我打算使用轨迹簇——用统计学的思维方式
Back to scratch. I'm going to use rays – with a statistical mindset.
我还要想办法用上我的网格 请看我操作
And I wanna use my grid – somehow! This is how I made it.
轨迹分段加插值会降低精度 所以我要使用不间断追踪器
Remember: ray segments plus interpolation crushes accuracy, so I use non-stop tracers.
可以通过调整相空间中点的随时间的更新方式调整它们的精度
And by tuning the phase point updates, I control their accuracy.
原理如下: 时间积分按一定规则调整位置和速度
This is how it works: The time integration shifts position and velocity via rules.
加速度改变速度 而速度又会改变位置
Acceleration changes velocity, which itself changes location.
考虑最简单的情况
Take the simplest form.
如果只使用当前位置的值 那么更新值就是个简单乘积 (前向欧拉法)
If you keep the current values constant over a time step, the update is a product.
缩短时间步长能减少误差累积
Reduce the time step, and you reduce the error accumulation.
但这样效率低
But that's inefficient.
高阶方法通过结合多次测试的结果
校注: 实际上不是多次"测试"
而是多次调用常微分方程右边的f
"测试"这个词隐含了"测试"结果有物理意义
但实际上完全可以是没有的 只是用来消去泰勒展开的高阶项
可能是作者自己有误解
Higher-order methods, using a mashup of test shots,
能以更低的计算成本获得类似的精度
give similar accuracy with less computational cost.
我们还能更进一步
But you can do better.
还记得相空间内概率的移动吗? 它的体积保持不变
Remember how the probability moved in phase space? It conserved volume.
至少在系统中能量守恒时是如此
At least when the system itself conserves energy.
如果积分器能利用这一特性 就会得到更长时间的演算精度优势
So, if you make your integrator share this property, you get better long-time behavior.
那要怎样做到体积保持不变呢?
But how to make it volume-conserving?
观察经典的一阶方法如何随着时间的推移调整方框的
Look how the classical 1st order method pushes this box over time steps.
位置和速度的同时调整让方框变大
The simultaneous shifts in position and velocity make the box bigger.
因此 应当改为交错调整位置和速度
So instead, make staggered shifts along position and velocity.
诀窍在于将每次更新分为两次体积守恒的剪切运动
The trick is to split the update in volume-conserving shear motions.
由于本例中加速度与速度无关 因此这种方法是可行的
校注: 加速度与速度有关也可以使用辛格式 只不过此时辛格式是隐式的
Which here works since the acceleration is independent of the velocity.
这样的剪切不会改变体积
It won't stretch while shearing!
这种方法称为辛算法 在长时间大步长下有明显优势
And this so-called symplectic integration gives great long-time behavior.
我并不是说辛算法是必用的
Now, I'm not saying you should always use symplectic integration.
非辛的算法达到足够高的精度 自然是辛的
校注: 原作可能想说的是无限精度高的积分即实际上的精确解肯定是辛的
但辛性质不会在高阶算法中自然出现
不是阶数够高算法本身就是辛的
A non-symplectic integrator ramped up to high accuracy fulfills symplecticity naturally.
两种算法都会收敛于实际情况 只是方法不同
Both types converge to the ground truth, just differently.
喂给积分器的系统信息也是越多越好
And the more information about the system you bake into the integrator, the better.
如果在行星际场景中存在微弱的相互作用
Split in Kepler orbit and interplanetary interaction steps if you have weak interactions in planetary scenarios.
可以把开普勒轨道与行星际相互作用拆分开来
让算法适配你的问题
Make it fit your problem!
为了让我的追踪器模拟航天器 我激活了随机点火和有限燃料
Now, to let my tracers mimic spaceships, I activate randomly firing and limited fuel.
它们还会分裂来填补空白
They also spawn offsprings to fill in the gaps.
我的网格中还限制了相空间中航天器的密度 这样也限制了计算时间
And I built a grid that limits the spaceship density in phase space and so the computational time.
这就是我的网格啦
There is my grid! :)
轨迹在前进 网格值在调整
So the rays explore, and the grid prunes.
很不错 但最终会有数百万条轨迹 计算成本还是很高
That's all great, but eventually, you send millions of rays. Which is costly.
这时统计的特性派上用场了
And that's where the statistical nature helps.
别忘了 预测是很难的 微小初值的改变会产生巨大影响
Remember: predictions are hard, and slight nudges make huge impacts.
所以 当发现有那么一点点可能的轨迹时
So, at least when getting first inspiration for possible routes,
就别在随机点火的前提条件下还强求预测的准确性了
why bother predicting accurately when you fire randomly anyway.
数值误差很容易过度补偿
Numerical errors are easily overcompensated.
只要保证低精度小云能覆盖住精确的那个就好了
Just make sure the less accurate blob covers the exact one.
您可以自己提高点火力度 或采取其他更有创意的全局措施
You can artificially crank up the firepower or take other creative global measures.
总之到最后 修改小云的全局行为可能比让所有追踪器变精确更快
Ultimately, modifying the blob's global behavior can be faster than making all tracers accurate.
这样粗略的计算可能会产生过度乐观的小云结果
This cheaply generates an over-optimistic blob evolution,
但其中一定会包含最优路径
but it definitely contains the winner route.
这意味着你在相空间中极大缩小了寻找精确解的范围
Which means you drastically limit the phase space portion where to look for the exact solution!
过滤掉不可能的路径 让之后路径的优化可以更轻松
Filtering impossible routes and optimizing promising candidates is easily in post.
⑦ 试飞
Step 7: Testflight
不是说他 但我这个朋友在月球附近到底在怎么飞?
I'm not judging, but what on earth is my friend doing near the Moon?
总之 回家其实并不难
Anyway, getting home is probably a cakewalk.
我们先来计算一下连续点火发动机的可达性
Let's compute the reachability for a continuously firing engine first.
动画进行了夸张处理 以表现其机动
Which I made comically strong to highlight the maneuvers.
并记住 我们只需追踪相空间小云的边界就能找到最快的返回路径
And remember: we just need to trace the phase space blob's boundary to find the quickest way home.
所以在计算网格中 我可以删除小云中央的追踪点
So, in the counting grid, I can delete the tracers inside.
而为了实验 计算中的航天器有无穷的耐热性
And just for this experiment, I made the spaceship ultra heat resistant.
只要能到达蓝星 多强的气动刹车都可以
It allows for hefty aerobraking – and reaching Blue's position is here enough.
(虽然看起来被填充，实际上还是相空间中区域的"边界")
而实际记录时 相空间小云边界在位置空间的投影就像一个被填充的区域
And for the records, the projection of a phase space blob's boundary looks like a filled region in position space.
开始运行
And now, let's run it.
你看 边界追踪解答了一个非常具体的问题
There you have it: boundary tracing answers a very specific question.
如何在连续点火的情况下尽快回家? 这就是答案
How to get home as quickly as possible under continuous firing? That's how!
相对月球 逆向点火 直到显著飞离月球引力影响
Fire prograde relative to Moon to screw out of Moon's gravitational significance.
等开始向蓝星坠落时
And once you fall down to Blue,
我以为持续相对蓝星反向点火会最高效地消耗轨道能量
I thought continuous retrograde firing eats up the orbital energy most efficiently.
或者持续相对蓝星逆角动量方向点火会更好一点
Or maybe firing against the angular momentum works better.
有点像飞离月球的反向操作
Kind of like the inverse of the maneuver for leaving Moon.
但结果却却出人意料地优雅
But the solution is surprisingly elegant.
别忘了 条件允许我们直接撞上蓝星 而代码也清楚这点
Remember, I allowed for crashing into Blue, and the code takes me at my words.
所以 实际结果是一部分逆向点火 但又有一点向右偏
So, it fires a little retrograde, but there is an overlayed firing to the right.
而它虽然没有在第一时间返回蓝星 但总体而言也快得多
And it gets home, not in the first encounter, but in the end much faster!
这个思路是 如果选择缓慢削弱角动量 并在第一圈中飞掠
The idea is: if you slowly chew up the angular momentum and still miss at the first encounter,
并准备在第二圈中尝试再入蓝星
prepare yourself to at least make it in the second attempt.
同时 电推发动机的推力有限
And since the electrical engine can only push so much,
航天器需要更多时间削弱角动量 导致航天器被送入更高的轨道
it needs a little bit more time and lever to do so, which it gets by swinging to a higher altitude.
这样 第一次飞跃的低效换来更多时间削弱角动量 从而能直接落入蓝星
So, being less efficient at the first encounter gives more time to fight the angular momentum and crash home.
那如果这样的机动很好用 为什么离开月球的时候不这样?
Now, if this maneuver is so great, why didn't we leave Moon that way?
很简单 因为我们不是从一条坠落的轨道离开月球的 而是圆轨道
Well, simply because we didn't start in an anti-crashing trajectory but in a circular orbit,
因此 对于连续点火来说 螺旋飞离是最快的办法
for which screwing out is the fastest way when firing continuously.
而对于着陆 无穷的热限制可以让我们以走这种"实验性"的轨迹
But when landing, heat resistance allowed for this rather "experimental" approach.
令人惊讶的是 该方法适用于常方向点火的情况
校注: 这里的常方向点火与 19:55 处借助太阳引力的弹道捕获有一定相似性
Surprisingly, it still works when holding the firing direction constant.
这相当于为一艘不点火的航天器虚构一个新的势能
This basically fakes a new potential for a virtually non-firing spaceship.
就像是画面中倾斜版的扭曲平面模型
It's like the classical rubber-sheet model tilted.
我的代码仅仅通过无脑推算数百万个追踪 就找到了这个路径
And my codes found this recipe simply by pushing millions of dumb tracers around.
总之 网格的边界没那么严格
Anyway, the gridded boundary has some thickness.
多观察附近的追踪结果 回家的路径还是很灵活的
So, checking nearby tracers; you're quite flexible in getting home.
而且这是一种数值全局求解方法 可以给你一个最优解的大致思路
And don't forget it's a numerical global solution method. It gives a winner inspiration.
稍后经过微调的路径会更好
The route gets better by fine-tuning later.
很有趣 但……对于非连续 单次大推力的点火怎么办?
Now that was fun, but … What about non-continuous, stronger firings?
我们可以把逻辑设为更强的连续随机点火 并结合推进剂断供
We could use stronger, continuous random firing combined with a propellant cut-off logic.
但追踪所有"理论可能"的路径会极大增加计算量
But tracing out all 'technically possible' paths really bows up the blob.
所以我在决定何时点火更有效这方面加了点小技巧
That's why I add a little bit of sanity by firing when it is beneficial.
想要理解"何时更有效" 我把航天器射入画面中的一维势阱中
And to see this benefit, I shoot one-dimensional spaceships into this potential well.
势阱中 相空间的相流很快发生变形
Here, the phase space paths quickly start to squeeze.
因为速度慢的航天器会在势阱中停留更长时间
This is because slower spaceships spent more time in this well.
它们加速的时间更长 速度的变化更多
They are accelerated for longer, building up more velocity change.
由于在这里能量是守恒的 因此每条路径的单位质量能量都是恒定的
And since energy is here conserved, each path is of constant energy per unit mass.
顺便 在这个参照系中 势阱是不会移动的
By the way, in this reference frame, the well doesn't move.
因此 速度和动能都是相对于势阱而言的
So velocity and kinetic energy are relative to that well.
对于点火 我们假设所有工质在一瞬间喷出发动机
Now, while firing, let's say all the reaction mass pushed by the engine is just one big mass pushed all at once.
再简化一点 我们假设喷出质量与剩余质量相等
In fact, let's make both masses equal for simplicity.
这样 点火相当于将大质量物体分解成两个相同小质量物体
Then, firing splits the big mass into two smaller masses,
两者会有一个固定的相对速度 之后沿各自路径行进
each following their own path, initially differing by a fixed relative velocity.
显然 想要获取最大的效益
Obviously, to get the most bang for the buck,
就要在相流最密集的地方"分离" 才能更容易来到高能量的地方
make the split when you can jump as much energy levels as possible, which is during the squeezing.
它们是每条路径上速度最快的点 此时动能最容易提升
There are the points of highest speed along each path, where kinetic energy climbs easiest.
奥伯特效应就是指在势阱中点火来实现最终的加速或减速
The final speed-up or slow-down merely by firing within a potential well is the Oberth effect.
如果初始速度高 那么奥伯特效应就会削弱
Now, if you start out at higher velocity, the Oberth contribution shrinks.
这也很好理解:
And this makes sense:
通过势阱太快 加速时间太少 难以建立更大的速度变化
passing so quickly, there is not enough time to accelerate much and build up greater velocity changes.
相流的"压缩"在高初始速度的情况下会被削弱
And so the squeezing fades for higher initial speeds.
就像势阱变更平坦了一样
It's like leveling the well.
飞跃陨石相比飞跃行星 奥伯特效应会更弱
When passing a rock instead of a planet, there is less Oberth effect.
另一方面 时间就是我们的优势
On the other hand, taking your time is beneficial.
因此 捕获与逃逸的路径对奥伯特效应非常敏感
That's why the capture/escape path is super sensitive to the Oberth effect.
画面中是接近逃逸的路径
That's the path that barely escapes.
而无论哪条路径 在速度最快的地方点火总是很有效的
Nonetheless, along each path, it's always beneficial to fire at the fastest point.
同时 我们还可以发射一块小云来获得更可视化的理解
And you get an intuitive visualization by shooting non-firing blobs.
它还能成为类似"变形感知"的工具
This makes it somewhat of a squeezing detection tool.
因为相空间内体积不变 速度方向的压缩意味着位置方向的膨胀
Since the phase space volume doesn't change, velocity-squeezing means position expansion.
势阱内也同理 变形最大的地方就是速度最快的地方
Apply it inside the well?! Once again, most squeezing is at the fastest point.
下一个问题 如何把它转换到二维空间?
Now, the question is, how does it translate to the two-dimensional case?
意思差不多啦
It's quite similar!
首先我们选几条相同近拱点的路径
First, let's take paths that share the same point of closest encounter.
假定我们都在速度最快的这一点进行点火
This connects them at their point of highest velocity via a single burn.
这对稍后的对比很有用
That's great for later comparison.
因此 在每条路径的最慢点射出大小相同的小云
So, shooting-off blobs that have the same size at each path's slowest point,
就可以观察到速度最快时有最大程度的变形
you see the highest stretching at the fastest point.
在此处点火 会最有效地调整能量
Firing here splits the energy most effectively.
我在图表中对比了在最快处点火与最慢处点火
So, in the diagrams, I compare firing at the fastest and the slowest point.
这就是奥伯特效应
This is the Oberth effect.
可以看出 几种路径中 抛物线的效率最高
Now, you can tell: among the paths, the parabola is most effective.
原因来自于各个路径中最慢的点在哪
And the reason simply comes down to where the slowest point is.
椭圆轨道 最慢点在远拱点
On an ellipse, it is the outmost point.
在速度最快的点点火 远拱点提升 远拱点速度降低
And the more you fire at the fastest point, the more it moves away, and the velocity lowers.
直到进入抛物线轨道 无穷远点速度为零 此时处于几乎逃逸的状态
Until you get a parabola with zero velocity at infinity – that's the route that barely escapes.
再加速一点点 就会得到双曲线轨道 此时无穷远点速度不为零
Fire more, and you get hyperbolas with non-zero velocity at infinity.
所以 由于椭圆轨道与双曲线轨道在最慢点的速度不为零
And that's it: Having non-zero velocity at the slowest points,
在它们最远点处点火仍有更多动能变化的空间
ellipses and hyperbolas give you more kinetic energy when firing on their worst side.
这就抵消了奥伯特效应
This counters the Oberth effect.
此时仍能看到能量的变化
You can still see a huge absolute energy increase.
但这个变化即使没有奥伯特效应 也相当可观了
But it would be huge already, even without the Oberth effect.
当然 抛物线上点火后双曲线的能量
And, of course, arriving on a parabola, the post-firing hyperbola
不会高于原本就是双曲线的点火后能量
won't have the highest energy compared to hyperbolic arrivals.
但遵守奥伯特效应仍是最有效率的
But the Oberth effect is "most effective."
所以我的模拟中会尽量在接近天体时向速度方向点火
So, in my simulation, I fire stronger aligned with the velocity vector closer to the planet.
希望能在数百万条路径中找到最优组合
And I hope millions of routes show the best combination.
毕竟抛物线轨道可不是遍地都是
You cannot always approach close to a parabola.
回到我朋友的话题: 我们来试试重返月球!
Now, back to my friend: let's get back to Moon!
小云迅速扩散在整个相空间中 计算上百万种可能路路径 简直一团乱麻
The blob quickly explores phase space, working on millions of possible routes, and … I can't see anything!
所以 出于科普目的 我给大家简化一下
So, just for learning, I give you something better.
假设近蓝星轨道每一点都有一个航天器
Let's sit on a Low Blue Orbit everywhere at once.
同时记住 利用奥伯特效应 我要点火两次
And remembering the Oberth effect, I will fire twice.
一次离开蓝星 一次在接近月球时点火 其余再无点火
One firing to get away from Blue and another firing to get captured by the Moon – nowhere in between.
顶视图可以看出初次点火的能量有几种
On top, I vary the initial fire strength.
每条环上都有无数航天器 以颜色区分点火强度
Each of these rings are millions of spaceships, colored by strength.
过不久 我们来到月球
Very soon, we hit Moon.
此时 我们可以进行第二次点火 被月球捕获
And here, we could make the second firing to get captured by the Moon.
这组路径就是霍曼转移轨道 进入月球的顺行或逆行轨道
This family of routes is the Hohmann transfer for a prograde or retrograde orbit around Moon.
燃料消耗非常大 但转移时间短 第一次与月球交会就抵达了
It's pretty expensive fuel-wise but quite fast: it's the first hit.
但我们继续模拟
But let's keep going.
每当这些线条与月球相交 就会进行点火 产生新的一组轨道
Every time the lines intersect with Moon, a firing would conclude a family of routes.
不胜枚举 甚至无法完全展现它们
And there are a lot of them – I cannot even show them all!
但其中有一组轨道值得大家注意
But there is one type of family that should draw your attention.
这一组线条慢慢接近月球
These lines slowly approach Moon.
直到一些轨迹不经任何点火就自动被月球弹道捕获
Until some tracers get ballistically captured by Moon without any firing.
答案路径有了 但还不知道是怎么算出来的
Now, seeing the winner route doesn't tell you why it is possible in the first place.
有意思的来了
And this is really cool.
我们重新跑一次弹道轨迹 并注意画面中高亮的部分
Let's rerun the ballistic trajectory, and I want you to focus on this section here.
发现了吗 打出的是椭圆轨道 但路径却向一侧拉宽了
You see it? We shoot off on an ellipse, but instead of sticking to it, we get pulled aside.
形状很像之前连续点火计算结果的逆向版本
Looks pretty much like the inverse of the continuous firing solution we found before.
可我们在这里并没有点火呀 是谁在拉扯我们?
But we don't fire here! So where does it come from?
想不到吧 是太阳在变相给我们"点火"
Surprise, surprise: it's the Sun – nature fires for us!
理解的第一步 先考虑势能
To get a first overview, draw the potential energy!
可以看出 离蓝星越近 动力学就越受蓝星主导
And you clearly see: close to Blue, most of the local dynamics are governed by Blue.
离蓝星越远 引力的影响就越偏向太阳
And the farther you go outwards, the more the collective gravitational pull shifts towards the Sun.
所以我们的轨迹就不再遵循二体问题中的椭圆了
That's why we don't stick to the two-body ellipse.
这段旅途的前半部分
In this first swing of the journey,
蓝星与月球引力减弱 太阳引力逐渐占据优势
the Sun gets more relevant, and especially the Blue-Moon interplay gets less relevant.
用一个简单的模型概括——圆型限制性三体问题
And there is a simple model that "captures" this: the restricted circular three-body model.
这是个非常好的例子 有丰富的动力学结构 可以解释很多问题
It's a great playground with already rich dynamical structures that explain a lot.
现在研究太阳始终朝同一方向运动的情况 将参照系同向旋转
Now, to study the motion with the Sun always in the same direction, co-rotate the reference frame.
这种视角的改变会改变以共转坐标书写的航天器运动方程的形式
This change in perspective alters the form of the equations of spaceship motion when written in co-rotating coordinates.
如何改变?
By how much are they altered?
需要让新的运动从"外面"看是"正确"的
Exactly as needed so that the generated motion looks correct from "the outside."
我举个例子
I give you an example.
画面中 我从一个包含移动和旋转的参照系来观察静止物体
Here, I look at a resting mass from a moving and rotating reference frame.
从这个视角观察 物体就好像在不停移动
From that perspective, the mass seems to get pushed around.
因此 在这个加速参照系中计算 必须增加一些力
So, computing in this accelerating reference frame, you have to add some forces.
在反向变换后 这些力要与移动物体的力相同 才能让物体看起来静止
Which combined push exactly as needed to look like resting after back-transformation.
因此 由于我们改变了参考系 同时出于运动学的原因 要增加一些力
So, these forces only pop up for kinematic reasons – once we mess with the coordinates.
描述的仍是同一运动 但视角选择得更巧妙了
You describe the same physical motion after all – just from a fancy-dancy perspective.
只是其中一些视角是有益的
But, as it goes, some of this mess is beneficial.
画面中 彼此旋转的两个物体同时受到重力影响
Here, the gravitational forces keep both masses on circular orbits.
观察其中的小质量物体
And focus on the smaller mass here.
如果视角与物体旋转的速度相同
Once co-rotating with the same rotational speed,
离心力就会刚好让物体受力平衡
the centrifugal force makes the mass apparently force-free.
实际上 只要输入某个位置 就可以计算出此处离心力
In fact, you can compute the centrifugal force anywhere by plugging in some position.
因此 我们可以将其视为来自与质量成比例的"下坡"方向的分力
So, we can see it as a downhill push coming from a position-based potential scaled with the mass.
重力势能也可同样处理
And we can do the same with the gravitational potential.
然后 把两者组合起来 就是"等效位能"
Obviously, bake them into an effective potential.
这就是航天器眼中这个共转参考系的势能图
That's the potential the spaceship sees in this co-rotating reference frame.
虽然物体仍受科里奥利力的影响
It's still pushed by the Coriolis force,
但等效位能可以为一个已知能量确定一个固定的可达性边界
but the effective potential gives a hard reachability limit for a given energy.
即 已知能量的无点火的小云 位置不会超过其零速度边界
And so, a non-firing blob never exceeds the zero-velocity lines for a given energy level.
这样 小云就被锁定在某块能量区域中
You can lock the blobs to certain energetic regions.
这种等效位能是一个极好的预测工具 用处可不止这些
This potential is a great predictive tool. And you can do even more.
显然 物体可以在共转参考系中的拉格朗日点保持静止
Apparently, you can sit at the stationary Lagrange points to rest in the co-rotating system.
我们轻轻推一下画面中的这个点
Let's isolate this point here and kick forward.
科里奥利力立即让它速度方向偏右
The Coriolis force immediately pushes to the right of the relative velocity.
最终 我们飞离了原来的点
Eventually, we drift off.
但假如我们在拉格朗日点旁边 以合适的力量推动
But if we start next to the Lagrange point and shoot off just right,
就会让物体进入环绕拉格朗日点的轨道
we can balance both forces to orbit around the Lagrange point.
某种程度上 我的代码就是这样计算这条轨道的
In a way, this is how my code computes this orbit.
点火时 以轨道的周期性为奖励函数 调整初始推力确定轨道
The shooting method tweaks the kick-off to nail down this orbit by rewarding periodicity.
对于这种对称的轨道 只要找到垂直于对称轴的路径就好
And for this symmetric orbit type it's enough to look for perpendicular axis crossings.
而且找出一个就能找出更多
Now, when there is one orbit, there are more.
不但要调整初始速度 还要调整初始位置 也就是调整相空间中的点
Tweaking not just the kick-off velocity but the location as well, meaning the whole phase space point,
从而得到不同的轨道
you land on a different orbit.
其中只需强制周期性 外加同上一圈轨道的一些距离测量
Just enforce periodicity and some distance measure towards the last orbit.
然后执行"数值延拓"
Then you performed 'numerical continuation'.
就能得到问题的一个解 这里是一个轨道的相点
You have a solution point of a problem - here a phase space point of an orbit,
然后找到相邻轨道的相点
and you find points on neighbor orbits.
对这些的轨道进行数值追踪 可以发现很难在这些轨道上停留
Now, tracing such an orbit numerically, you can check it's hard to stay on them.
它们把相空间分成几块区域
They are surrounded by regions in phase space that,
身处其中的物体会被引向轨道或远离轨道——对应稳定与不稳定流形
once you sit on them, lead you to the orbit or away from it – stable or unstable manifolds.
这就是我在寻找的结构
These are the structures I'm looking for.
因为它们能告诉我们未来轨迹的走向
Why? Because they tell you in advance what you get.
观察一维势垒中的航天器
Take the one-dimensional spaceship with a hill-shaped potential.
从任一点出发 相点总会沿相流运动
Starting anywhere makes you follow the flow.
从平衡点出发 则一动不动
Starting at the equilibrium leads you nowhere.
这一点并不算一个轨道 但我们假设它等效于 停在这里的点会一直保持
This point is not an orbit, but let's pretend it is equivalent as in: once you sit on it, you stay on it.
相空间里各种运动中的不动点
A stationary feature of the phase space motion.
而稳定流形和不稳定流形就是相空间中往返这个点的曲线
And the stable and unstable manifolds are nothing more but curves that lead you to and from that point.
虽然无法到达 需要无穷大的时间
Though you never reach it, it would take an infinite amount of time.
但流形仍是有用的 它能告诉你附近相流的一些性质
But they are helpful as they tell you what happens close to them.
你能预知 靠近稳定流形运动 最终会走向任意一支不稳定流形
You know in advance that once you ride close to the stable manifold,
you will curve away, following either side of the unstable manifold.
它们就像相空间中移运动的主干一样
That's the skeleton of the phase space motion.
此外 路径稍有不同 可能就会在抵达同一终点时花费更长的时间
Also, taking slightly different paths is great to generate some waiting time while ending up at the same location.
这两点对规划航天飞行非常有用
Both points are great for planning a spaceflight.
因为想要与月球交会 你需要在正确时间正确位置有正确的速度
Remember: to catch up with Moon, you need the right position and velocity at the right time.
无论你初始能量有多高
And no matter how energetic you start out,
最终总要想办法积累环绕蓝星的角动量
you need to build up angular momentum relative to Blue as well.
也因此 霍曼转移的第二次点火很消耗能量
That's why the Hohmann transfer comes with a strong second burn.
但流形可以告诉我们一个免费的解
But the manifolds tell us how to get it for free.
一部分稳定流形直接延伸到蓝星
Part of the stable manifold reaches down to Blue.
航天器可以沿着稳定流形 拥有足够能量 但角动量不高
You can follow close to it, having enough energy but still low angular momentum.
但观察不稳定流形 我们知道早晚有条正确的"路子"
But looking at the unstable manifold, we know there must be the right "curve away"
把我们带到有更高角动量的时候
bringing us up here in time – having much more angular momentum.
这幕后的手 就是等效位能与科里奥利力
Under the hood, it's the effective potential and the Coriolis force pushing us.
还能注意到 我们的路径其实很接近稳定流形的外侧
Also note: we curve away close to the outside of the stable manifold tube.
大家猜猜保持在稳定流形内会怎样?
You can guess what happens being inside the tube.
现在我们有了角动量 该在适当时候与月球交会了
Now, having the angular momentum, we need to approach Moon just right,
但图中流形描述的是太阳-蓝星-航天器三体系统
which doesn't even exist in the three-body system where these manifolds come from.
当航天器靠近蓝星月球 其限制性三体系统的流形会慢慢起主导作用
Well, closer to Blue and Moon, their restricted three-body system with its manifolds is more relevant.
所以我们这里要切换用到的流形 沿着稳定流形前往月球
So, hopping manifolds is the name of the game – and we follow the stable manifold to the Moon.
统计上看 与月球交会时 一些追踪会被暂时捕获几个周期
Now, approaching Moon statistically, some tracers get temporarily captured for a number of cycles.
我们系统地了解一下其中本质
And to get the essence of this, go ahead systematically.
所有轨迹都会有一次最近的交会点
Any passing trajectory has a point of its first closest encounter.
因此我们可以假设以垂直某条径向线的角度出发 画面中是顺向轨道
And so you start at an angle with a perpendicular kick-off – here in prograde direction.
如果没有蓝星 你会进入一条带偏心率的椭圆轨道
If it wouldn't be for Blue, you would then make an ellipse with a predefined eccentricity.
但因为蓝星掺了一脚 我们统计一下逃逸月球前绕行了多少圈
But since Blue spits in the soup, count the number of revolutions around Moon until escape.
为此 每次绕行后 返回径向线时检查航天器-月球系统开普勒能量的正负
For that, you check the Kepler energy sign of the local spaceship-Moon system after each revolution.
即 n-稳定 的轨道会绕月球飞 n 圈 其间开普勒能量为负
So, n-stable orbits make n revolutions around Moon with a negative energy sign at the cut section,
并且它们都会在绕蓝星一整圈以上的时候终止继续计算
all without making a full revolution around Blue. That's the simulation cut-off time.
沿径向线上其他点重复该实验 会发现 n-稳定性 的变化
Repeat this experiment for the next points along the cut section, and you find changes in the n-stability.
重点观察 0-稳定 与 1-稳定 的轨道及它们的边界
Now, let's focus on 0- and 1-stable orbits and their boundaries.
对于给定的初始偏心率 所有角度上这些边界点的集合即为弱稳定边界
These boundary points collected for all angles for the given eccentricity make the weak stability boundary.
沿着这条边界 发现上面有些点会让我们落向月球
And along this boundary, you find points that will crash into Moon.
这些点有两大优点
Now, these sets of points are great for two reasons:
首先 很明显 它们会告诉你在相空间的哪些位置会被月球捕获
First, obviously, they tell you where to be in phase space to get captured by Moon.
这与等效位能和流形的思路类似
This is similar to the effective potential and manifold ideas.
其次 虽然有时与流形的点重合 但弱稳定边界是一种更通用的工具
Second, while sometimes coinciding with manifold points, they make a more general tool.
流形是个好东西 分割了能量区域
Manifolds are great; they split energetic regions,
让人很容易就能看到物体出入的位置
making it easy to see where stuff goes in and goes out.
但它们需要轨道来产生
But they need orbits to emerge from.
而轨道需要拉格朗日点来产生
And the orbits need Lagrange points to emerge from.
而这些拉格朗日点需要从圆型限制性三体系统中产生
And these Lagrange points here need the restricted circular three-body system to emerge from.
如果换成限制性四体系统
When you go with a restricted four-body system,
拉格朗日点和新的结构就不复存在了
the Lagrange points and the emerging structures are no more.
其中三体的子系统会受到其余质量的干扰
The three body sub-systems are disturbed by the remaining mass.
因此 你并不能完全静止在共转参照系中
And so you don't exactly rest in the co-rotating reference frame.
不过其中仍然存在敏感区域 流形仍可作为很好的参考
But there are still sensitive regions, and the manifolds still make a great guide.
而弱稳定边界可以直接从更一般的系统中建立
The weak stability boundary – you can build it for more general systems directly.
无论用什么方法 只需计算绕行次数就行
You simply count revolutions – however, they came about.
它现在只依赖于时间了
It's just time-dependent now.
不过老天爷都给你送来了 你就点个火留下来吧
But honestly, if nature gently carries you close to Moon, fire a little bit to safely stay with it.
这样就直接来到 n-稳定性 了
That's how you blow up the n-stability.
你可以从偏心轨道的 1-稳定性 直接来到圆轨道的 10⁺-稳定性
You jump from the 1-stability for the eccentric approach to the above 10-stability for the circular orbit.
画面中是前往月球的低能量转移轨道的相空间结构……去哪都行
These are the phase space structures for low-energy transfer to the Moon – or anywhere else.
从近蓝星轨道点火来到画面这里的轨道
Starting from a Low Blue Orbit fire to get up here.
然后沿着稳定流形行进 然后蹿入不稳定流形中
Then, follow inside the stable manifold tube and slip through the orbit into the unstable manifold.
运气好说不定能跑到黄星的稳定流形中呢
If we are lucky, it overlaps with the stable manifold of planet Yellow.
可惜不能 两者离得太远了
But we aren't. They don't even come close.
我们让画面中的垂直方向表示速度 可以看出两者在相空间中差了多远
Visualizing the speed by an upward shift, you can guess the phase space distance.
所以需要找一个高效的两次点火转移
So, you look for a cost-effective two-burn hop-over.
这就是行星间的霍曼转移
That's an intermediate Hohmann transfer.
从这里开始到近黄星轨道 就是前述过程的逆向了
From here on, it is the inverted sequence to a Low Yellow Orbit.
这一圈圈的流形结构就是星际运输网络
This sequence of manifolds is part of the interplanetary transport network.
看着花里胡哨 但怎么确定它比传统霍曼转移更好?
Now, as fancy as it looks, it's hard to see if it's better than a classical Hohmann transfer.
我用一个更直观的蓝星-月球例子来说明这样的路线可能消耗更小
So, let me convince you with a much more intuitive Blue-Moon example that such routes can be cheaper.
既然我们只要到月球就行
Remember: Since, all we got to do is getting up here,
那我们就借用一下月球自己的引力弹弓吧
let's get there via gravity assist by Moon itself.
霍曼转移需要一次强力的制动点火才能被月球捕获
The Hohmann transfer would need a strong retrograde burn to get captured by Moon.
而低能量弹道转移可以无消耗被月球捕获 只是时间长了点
The low-energy ballistic transfer gets you captured for free. It just takes some time.
各有利弊
That's the trade-off.
公平起见 这条轨道最终都会进入 2-稳定 的捕获
And for a fair comparison, both missions lead here to a 2-stable capture.
另外 第四象限的科里奥利力和等效位能也对我们有利
Also, the Coriolis force and effective potential work in our favor in the fourth quadrant as well.
在这里 角动量得以持续有效积累
Here, the angular momentum keeps building up in the right way.
所以你可以使用类似的路径前往月球
So you can expect similar routes to the Moon.
你还可以选择内侧的路径
You can also use inner routes.
即利用霍曼转移或低推力螺旋进入蓝星-月球系内稳定流形
That's when you hop on Blue-Moon's inner stable manifold, either via a Hohmann transfer or the low thrust spiral.
这也能送你到月球
This carries you up to the Moon.
还有其他各种可能性 不同轨道族之间还有相互联系的地方
校注: 这里展示都是周期轨道没有拟周期轨道
李雅普诺夫轨道在限制性三体问题中一般指在一个平面上的周期轨道
给垂直于这个平面加上个同频率周期运动就可以叫晕轨道
And to show what else is possible, the orbit families we found are linked to other families.
我之前展示过的李雅普诺夫轨道 会分裂成晕轨道等等
The planar Lyapunov orbits – the ones I have shown before – bifurcate into Halo orbits and many more.
它们都有各自眼花缭乱的流形
Each having its own manifolds. It's a mess.
总之 它们都是很有用的工具
It's helpful, nonetheless.
虽然看上去犹如一团乱麻 你可能会怀疑到底行不行
Things seem cluttered from time to time, leaving you wondering if you ever make it:
一定行的!
there is always a way, always!
⑧ 该回家了
Step 8: Time to get home.
问题出现了:
This is the problem:
我的朋友已经消耗大量燃料在丝绸星上飞出大椭圆轨道来返回蓝星
My friend makes an elliptic orbit at planet Silk with enough propellant to reach planet Blue.
但剩余燃料不够进入近蓝星轨道了
But not enough to get into a circular Low Blue Orbit.
氧气有限 航天器结构也无法进行气动刹车
Oxygen is limited. And hull integrity is … we shouldn't aerobrake.
因此 为了消耗能量 我们需要些巧妙的引力弹弓 可能需要点火
So, to lose energy, we need clever swing-by's, possibly fired.
说到点火 离开丝带星的椭圆轨道上 在离星球最近的地方点火
Speaking of firing: On the first elliptic passage – firing closest to the planet
并不是相对于太阳的最佳出发角度
doesn't make the best departure angle relative to the Sun.
奥伯特效应带来的速度 并不一定指向行星运动轨迹反向
Not all of the Oberth speed boost goes in the backwards direction.
因此 最佳点火点通常经过一番妥协后其实效率不那么高
That's why the best firing point makes an inefficient compromise.
再等等就能获得更好的出发角度 还能飞到离太阳更近的地方
Simply waiting gives better departure angles, and you can reach "farther down."
但同样 行星相对位置必须满足条件才能有最好的引力弹弓效应
Then again, the planets must align for great swing-bys – that's a phasing problem.
我是这样解决的
This is how I made it.
我把空间分为行星际部分和行星系内的局部
I divided the space in an interplanetary part and local planetary parts.
它们控制追踪的分辨率
These control the tracer resolutions.
没有接触到蓝星的追踪都是未能按时抵达的
Now, the tracers without contact didn't make it to Blue in time.
所以最优解隐藏在画面中蓝星划过的阴影里
So, the winner route is hidden in the uninvestigated shadows.
我将用更高分辨率的采样记录这些阴影内的追踪
These I explore with higher resolution sampled from the recording.
最终 并对交会次数进行多次迭代
Eventually, I iterate along encounters.
在蓝星 一些轨迹已经可以用剩余燃料燃料减速进入目标轨道了
Now, at planet Blue, some tracers have enough propellant to decelerate onto the goal orbit.
这样一条完整的轨迹就形成了
That makes a complete route.
由于微小变化会产生巨大差异 因此每种轨道都可以得到无限多的路线
And since tiny changes make a huge difference, you get infinitely many routes per family.
只需从一众高效的结果中挑选一条合适的路线 权衡好时间和燃料即可
Simply pick a suitable route from an efficient cluster, trading time vs. propellant.
画面中这条路线绕丝绸星飞了五圈 然后前往内行星
This route makes five revolutions around planet Silk before leaving for the inner planets.
然后画面中一次蓝星的引力弹弓削弱了大量能量
Here, a swing-by at Blue takes away a lot of energy.
不过它仍需要额外的点火才能恰好飞入蓝星轨道
Still, it needs additional firing to make the final arc hit home just right.
如果你愿意花费更多旅行时间 可以尝试这条路线 消耗燃料更少
If you can invest more travel time, take this route and save even more propellant.
蓝星-黄星的引力弹弓可以削弱更多的能量
The Blue-Yellow double swing-by takes away even more energy.
然后只要坐等自己和蓝星交会就好了
And then just wait until you catch up with Blue.
两种方法都比瞬时点火的最优霍曼转移强得多
Both variants are much better than the instant and optimal Hohmann transfer.
与预想的一样 由于我鼓励利用奥伯特效应进行引力弹弓
And as expected, since I encouraged Oberth-promoting swing-bys,
几个最优结果大多包含局部的高效机动
the winners are mostly composed of locally efficient maneuvers.
如果把轨迹按飞掠的行星为分段 加以颜色区分
And if you color it not by cluster but by interplanetary segment, you get this.
那么引力弹弓次数越多 最后的轨道曲线就越接近蓝星轨道的形状
The more swing-bys you consider, the easier it is to get the final arc close to Blue's orbit.
从而更容易到达低能量的流形
Making it easier to arrive on a low-energy manifold.
顺便 这就是另一个我要解决的难题了
By the way, this is another riddle I'm trying to solve.
或许你们能帮我……如果大家喜欢这期视频的话?
Maybe you can help me with that … if you enjoyed the video?
感谢大家观看
Thank you for watching! Oberth and out.